<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>      
<!ENTITY rfc4287 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4287.xml'>      
<!ENTITY xmlns SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.W3C.REC-xml-names-19990114.xml'>      
<!ENTITY rdfsg SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.W3C.WD-rdf-syntax-grammar-20031010.xml'>      
]>
<rfc docName="draft-hanson-oauth-mfa-assoc-latest">
  <front>
    <title>OAuth 2.0 Multi-Factor Authenticator Association</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Hanson" fullname="Jared Hanson">
      <organization>Auth0 Inc.</organization>
      <address>       
        <email>jaredhanson@gmail.com</email> 
        <uri>http://www.jaredhanson.net/</uri>       
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <abstract>
      <t>This specification defines mechanisms for dynamically associating
        authenticators with resource owners.  Once associated, an authenticator
        can be used for strong authorization within OAuth 2.0.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        In order for an OAuth 2.0 authorization server to enforce strong
        authorization, it must associate resource owners with one or more
        authenticators capable of responding to a strong authorization
        challenge.  This specification describes how an authenticator can be
        dynamically associated with a resource owner to obtain this information.
      </t>
        
      <section title="Notational Conventions">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
          "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>
          This specification also defines the following terms:
          
          <list style="hanging"> 
          <t hangText="MFA Token:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A short-lived token representing an authorization session.</t>
          </list> 
        </t>
      </section>
        
    </section>
    
    <section title="Authenticator Associate Endpoint">
      <t>
        The authenticator associate endpoint is an OAuth 2.0 endpoint defined in
        this document that is designed to allow an authenticator to be
        associated with a resource owner.  The authenticator associate endpoint
        MUST accept HTTP POST messages with request parameters encoded in the
        entity body using the "application/json" format.  The authenticator
        associate endpoint MUST be protected by a transport-layer security
        mechanism.
      </t>
      <t>
        The authenticator associate endpoint MUST be an OAuth 2.0 protected
        resource and it MUST accept access tokens as defined by <xref target='RFC6750'/>
        to limit association to only previously authorized parties.  The method
        by which the access token is obtained by the client is generally out of
        band; two such mechanisms are defined by this specification.  The method
        by which the access token is verified and validated by the authenticator
        associate endpoint is out of scope for this specification.
      </t>
        
      <section title='Authenticator Associate Request' anchor="assoc-req">
        <t>
          The client makes a request to the authenticator associate endpoint by
          sending the following parameters with a content type of
          <spanx style='verb'>application/json</spanx>:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
            <t hangText='authenticator_types'>
              <vspace />
              OPTIONAL. Array of authenticator type strings that the client
              supports.  These authenticator types are defined as follows:
              
              <list style="symbols">
                <t><spanx style="verb">otp</spanx>: A device that generates
                one-time passwords.</t>
                
                <t><spanx style="verb">oob</spanx>: A device that communicates
                securely with the authorization server over a secondary
                channel.</t>
              </list>
              
              Authorization servers MAY allow for other values as defined in
              the authenticator type extension process.
            </t>
            <t hangText='oob_channels'>
              <vspace />
              OPTIONAL. Array of out-of-band channel strings that the client
              supports.  These out-of-band channels are defined as follows:
              
              <list style="symbols">
                <t><spanx style="verb">sms</spanx>: SMS channel to the user at
                a registered number.</t>
                
                <t><spanx style="verb">tel</spanx>: Telephone call to the user
                at a registered number.</t>
                
                <t><spanx style="verb">email</spanx>: E-mail sent to the user
                at a registered address.</t>
                
                <t><spanx style="verb">auth0</spanx>: Push notification to
                Guardian app on user's mobile device.</t>
                
                <t><spanx style="verb">duo</spanx>: Push notification to Duo
                Mobile app on user's mobile device.</t>
              </list>
              
              Authorization servers MAY allow for other values as defined in
              the out-of-band channel extension process.  This parameter is
              used when the client indicates support for authenticator types
              including the value "oob".
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The access token MUST be sent as a Bearer Token, per section 2 of
          <xref target='RFC6750'/>.  It is RECOMMENDED that the access token be
          sent using the Authorization header field.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            For example, the client makes the following HTTPS request (line
            breaks are for display purposes only)::
          </preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
POST /associate HTTP/1.1
Host: server.example.com
Authorization: Basic czZCaGRSa3F0MzpnWDFmQmF0M2JW
Content-Type: application/json

{
"authenticator_types": [
  "otp", "oob"
]
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
      
      <section title='Authenticator Associate Response' anchor="assoc-res">
        <t>
          If the associate request is valid and authorized, the authorization
          server selects an authenticator that the client is capable of
          supporting, and responds with an HTTP 200 OK status code and a body
          of type "application/json" with the following content:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
            <t hangText='bind_code'>
              <vspace />
              REQUIRED.  Bind code generated by the authorization server, used
              to complete binding of the authenticator to the user's account.
              The bind code MUST expire shortly after it is issued to mitigate
              the risk of leaks.  A maximum bind code lifetime of 10 minutes
              is RECOMMENDED.
            </t>
            <t hangText='authenticator_type'>
              <vspace />
              REQUIRED.  Authenticator type to associate with the user's
              account.
            </t>
            <t hangText='barcode_uri'>
              <vspace />
              OPTIONAL. URI to be rendered as a barcode which can be scanned
              by the authenticator to effect provisioning.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The response MAY include additional parameters that are interpreted
          according to an authenticator type definition.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4627"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6749"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6750"?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-oauth-discovery-05.xml'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
